<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2026-01-22T02:18:55+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Staff-level software engineer with 16 years of experience. API design, microservices, team leadership. Also a BJJ coach. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Just Get a Job!</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2022/just-get-a-job/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Just Get a Job!"/><published>2022-08-28T13:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-28T13:51:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2022/just-get-a-job</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2022/just-get-a-job/"><![CDATA[<p>In recent years I’ve seen many tweets like this one:[https://twitter.com/alicetweet/status/1562516853473230849</p> <p>Here’s a novel way to avoid that college “debt trap” - get a job while going to school.</p> <p>I’ve found this kind of response frustrating, as I believe it completely ignores the reality of student loan debt and taking a job while in school. As I am a graduate of Rutgers University, I would like to provide an example of how challenging ‘getting a job’ to cover your student loan debt is. Let’s take a look at getting a job at Rutgers New Brunswick, in the hopes of paying for your student loans.</p> <p>Costs and the Job</p> <p>First, I’d like to point out a significant barrier - it can be very difficult to find a job as a student. While positions are often open in college areas, competition is steep - there are many students looking for jobs. Anecdotally, my experience was that there were few decently-paying positions open at nearby restaurants at Rutgers. The only easily-available position was a telemarketing/sales position, which paid fairly poorly and did not provide a full-time position. This is still something, but it was the only such job of its kind at Rutgers. Thus, I’ve chosen to use a barista position in my example, as it is a position that reasonably approximates the kind of salary a student worker could expect.</p> <p>Based on the[Rutgers tuition estimates, the average in-state student needs to pay $30,172 per academic year. Note that this does not include rent / food / etc. for the summer (mid-May until September, ~3 and a half months) or the winter break (short, usually only a few weeks).</p> <p>[Based on some figures, the average incoming student receives only ~$3200 of scholarship aid in their first year. Being generous (and for easier calculations) let us assume that our example student receives $5000 in scholarship aid each year, resulting in a total bill of $25,000 / year that must be covered by loans or pay.</p> <p>A Barista</p> <p>[According to Indeed.com, the average pay for a Barista in NJ is $10.88 / hour. Let’s be generous and round up to $12.00 / hour, which is realistically the most a student would be able to find. Now, again, anecdotally, most baristas do not work a full 40 hours / week. This is quite often the case for students, as they will often not have the necessary availability to cover the full 40 hours.[There[appearsto be[plenty[of evidencethat baristas (and other, similar workers) receive less than 40 hours a week, on top of dealing with extremely inconsistent schedules and stressful work conditions. However, let’s assume that, at the very least, each worker will receive 32 hours of work a week for their weeks of employment.</p> <p>Let’s calculate:</p> <ul> <li> <p>weeks of work during school: ~37 weeks</p> </li> <li> <p>total hours worked at 32/week: 1,184</p> </li> <li> <p>total paid over this period at $12/hour:$14,208</p> </li> </ul> <p>Uhhh … that’s not enough. At a full 40 hours and $13/hour, we’re still only at ~$19k for the year. At a full 40 hours per week, at $13 / hour, and a full50 weeks of work, we reach $26,000 / year. This would cover JUST the ~9 months of school, and does not cover any other common costs:</p> <ul> <li> <p>costs of housing during the off season.</p> </li> <li> <p>costs of supplies or books, whichseems to average around $1300 / year.</p> </li> <li> <p>travel costs / commuting costs.</p> </li> </ul> <p>Conclusions</p> <p>[There is plenty of evidencethat most students[graduate with significant student loan debt- and almost a quarter graduate with significant (avg. ~$34,000) private debt, which comes with significantly less borrower protection than federal loan debt. The ‘just get a job’ response is ignorant of the realities facing students, and even agenerousapproximation of what such a job would provide in loan relief still indicates that students would leave school with large debts.</p> <p>In addition, this analysis does not account for other, common situations that students will find themselves in, all of which would result in an even larger gap between their education costs and their ability to pay:</p> <ul> <li> <p>inability to find full-time employment (thus receiving &lt;32 hours/week)</p> </li> <li> <p>inability to make their ideal salary (thus receiving &lt;$10.88/week)</p> </li> <li> <p>additional credits / semesters of schooling required</p> </li> <li> <p>economic downturns resulting in inability to find work</p> </li> <li> <p>economic reality of the campus area resulting in inability to find work</p> </li> <li> <p>study / class hour conflicts resulting in reduced employment hours</p> </li> </ul> <p>Tweets like the one at the top are, at best, ignorant of the realities facing students.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In recent years I’ve seen many tweets like this one:[https://twitter.com/alicetweet/status/1562516853473230849]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Post 617149812603846656</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2020/post-617149812603846656/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Post 617149812603846656"/><published>2020-05-04T03:38:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-04T03:38:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2020/post-617149812603846656</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2020/post-617149812603846656/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/blog/617149812603846656.png" alt="image"/></p> <p>Burnout</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The speed curve</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2019/the-speed-curve/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The speed curve"/><published>2019-06-16T22:36:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-06-16T22:36:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2019/the-speed-curve</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2019/the-speed-curve/"><![CDATA[<p>“Metrics” said the engineer. “We need metrics to measure our success”. And so velocity and predictability were born.</p> <p>One of the challenges of Scrum and Agile methodology are that there are no easy-to-grasp, rigid metrics that we can use to immediately evaluate ourselves and our projects. By encouraging a more fluid system of project management, we open ourselves up to never really understanding whether or not we did the right thing. Was it a good thing that we cancelled something in Beta 2 because we realized our beta testers were not happy with it? Or would it have been better if we’d hit faster deadlines for it, or finished out the whole project before showing it to customers that didn’t perfectly fit our target audience.</p> <p>In this post, I won’t get into the specifics of evaluating these end-goals. High-level decisions like project direction are one thing, but the minutia can be a bit easier to handle. For example, many teams use planning poker or similar methodology to estimate how much effort they are putting into their work. These estimates are used by managers and teams to determine if a team is successful or not.</p> <p>I’d like to talk about one of the problems I have with these metrics. I’d like to explain why I prefer more fluid metrics, even if those metrics require more human judgement to evaluate.</p> <p>Estimates being flaky is the first issue. Unless a team is very experienced with their codebase and has extremely good specifications, estimates about how much work a task takes are likely to differ wildly. Maybe editing a piece of copy or adding an image on the homepage of your platform can be consistently pointed as a ‘1′. But that task to add a column to your users table gets estimated as a ‘2′ by half of your engineers and a ‘5′ by the other half - some figure the change you’ll need to do to surface that UI element will take them a day, along with the QA steps needed to release it to production; others argue it will take only a few minutes, and that the testing can be accomplished much more quickly.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Metrics” said the engineer. “We need metrics to measure our success”. And so velocity and predictability were born.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Five Offboarding Tips</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/five-offboarding-tips/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Five Offboarding Tips"/><published>2018-08-22T12:35:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-08-22T12:35:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/five-offboarding-tips</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/five-offboarding-tips/"><![CDATA[<p>Having left my position at Hearst, I was responsbile for tranferring almost two years’ worth of knowledge to the tech leads that would replace me in a just a couple short weeks. This was a daunting task, but, while there were some hiccups, I think I was able to do so successfully. It required some forethought and a good place to store and share documentation, but at the end of the day just making sure to care about the process did the most good.</p> <p>Now that I’m through the process, I’d like to give a few tips as to how you can ensure the same process at your company, be it when you yourself leave or when someone else is getting ready to. Some of these will be tips for outside the actual offboarding process, as ensuring good offboarding means setting up good practices even during less turbulent times.</p> <ol> <li> <p>Have a single docs location that everyone on the team has access to.</p> </li> <li> <p>Schedule regular knowledge sharing sessions and deep-dives.</p> </li> <li> <p>Set up a ‘Q&amp;A’ section that everyone can post to.</p> </li> <li> <p>Quickly schedule knowledge shares for missing gaps.</p> </li> <li> <p>Assign an offboarding ‘point person’.</p> </li> </ol> <p>Having a single point where the whole team goes to for documentation is crucial in any organization, not just for the offboarding process. However, it may not be obvious how critical this is until a high-quality contributor leaves. Whatever the situtation, make sure that during this time, you make sure all the documentation related to this person leaving is moved to a single source of truth, and that everyone on the team that is participating in the transition process can easily get to it.</p> <p>Having this in place will guarantee that everyone stays focused on what is important - leaving behind a consise record of what is known, what is unknown, and where to go from here. Having multiple docs locations, or no clearly assigned spot, means someone may have to spend time reconstructing a web of relationships after the contributor leaves, which wastes time at best, or loses knowledge permanently at worst.</p> <p>This is another tip that can be implemented immediately, but one of the best ways you can ensure that losing someone doesn’t crush your productiviy or kill a team is to regularly schedule knowledge sharing sessions. One of the ways I’ve seen this happen is to schedule a weekly ‘developer chapter’ meeting, where engineers are encouraged to talk about and give presentations on work they have done recently on their teams, or even things they have learned or worked on during their spare time.</p> <p>Keeping well ahead of inevitable team changes is critical. One of the biggest benefits is that doing these sessions ahead of time means that the knowledge tends to be fresh. Scheduling these sessions only at the last minute means a contributor may be trying to remember design decisions or challenging problem solutions at a time when they are being bombarded with hundreds of other questions. It also means that the time spent offboarding can be left for the really tough questions - post-mortem-style questions like ‘what would you have done differently on this project’ or ‘what are the likely upcoming technical hurdles’ rather than minutia.</p> <p>One of the better ways to guarantee good knowledge transfer is to ask questions, and keeping those questions public is the best way to keep the flow going. Answering questions in a ‘Q&amp;A’ format is a good way to both sort through potential gaps in knowledge. It is also less intimidating for newer engineers or those less comfortable publicly asking for some of this information to contribute to the process in a meaningful way. You should periodically sort these questions into sections based on topic so that the end result isn’t an unwieldy wall of text, but on the whole even a less sorted list can be helpful.</p> <p>It’s most important to rapidly move the person leaving from doing work to moving knowledge to other people. One of the ways you can guarantee a big loss to your company is letting an engineer that is already leaving take all the knowledge they have accumulated, all the bugs they know exist and the tricks they have mastered to get around in your system, and leave without giving any of it away. While there may be important outstanding projects that need to be finished in the timeframe of this person moving on, a focus on getting down what can never be replaced is usually more important than knocking out a few extra tickets.</p> <p>This is a tip that is also most likely to change as circumstances on the ground change. If there are major feature planning sessions or really important pieces of functionality that are due immediately, it may be more important for this person to finish these tasks than to immediately start writing notes and docs. That said, it’s still often the right move to eat the producitivity hit and understand that some things will come in late. It also easier to account for a guaranteed miss on some deliverable than try to eke out a last few hours of work from someone whose productivity may already be on the downswing.</p> <p>The quickest way to get traction on any project is to assign someone to be the main shepherd of that work. Assigning a point person to be the go-to for the off-boarding process is useful for making sure nothing gets missed. It ensures that the teams remaining stay focused on their work and are minimally impacted by the transition process. It also means that the person being offboarded has a consistent line of communication to go through; any questions, issues that arise, or help this person needs to get things in order before leaving can be addressed to a single responsibly party.</p> <p>Keeping these lines of communications clear is important from both sides. It may be that management has many questions for the person leaving, as do other team leads. Having a dozen interrupting meetings with a variety of concerned workers will make it difficult for the person to focus on sharing their knowledge in a consise and consistent way. They may be distracted and miss important information, or say something verbally that is not written down, but missed later because it was ‘already said’.</p> <p>These tips are only the starting point of making your offboarding process a clean and enjoyable one. They serve to help you keep your relationship with the former employee intact, as well as make sure the company continues chugging along without losing a ton of productive time whenever someone decides to leave. With the[tech industry hitting an average attrition rate of 23%, it’s important to plan for this inevitability. I hope this leaves you with a good starting point, and gives you some ideas on how to better your own processses.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Having left my position at Hearst, I was responsbile for tranferring almost two years’ worth of knowledge to the tech leads that would replace me in a just a couple short weeks. This was a daunting task, but, while there were some hiccups, I think I was able to do so successfully. It required some forethought and a good place to store and share documentation, but at the end of the day just making sure to care about the process did the most good.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Proximity</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/proximity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Proximity"/><published>2018-07-30T12:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-30T12:17:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/proximity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/proximity/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the biggest challenges I’ve faced since I’ve moved from being an individual contributor to tech lead has been maintaining my opportunities to work with other senior engineers. My team has undergone significant changes and, as a result, I’m most often the senior member working on any particular feature. While this has had its benefits - mentorship and shared learning through teaching - it’s not the same as daily, 1:1 discussions with extremely experienced engineers.</p> <p>One of the main hurdles to jump in this pursuit is proximity. The floor our teams sit on is split in a very particular way, resulting in some teams sitting quite far away from their coworkers. While engineers still have many other coworkers to reach out to near them, this is enough of a substitute. Getting advice from someone who only vaguely knows what you are working on is very different from seeking the same advice from someone who is handling that code on a daily basis.</p> <p>Slack is certainly a tool that helps in this respect. It allows you to direct your questions to exactly the developers or team you need advice from. At the same time, the impedance of Slack, like most chat programs, is much greater than that of person-to-person speech. Even on teams that are very comfortable having all manner of difficult and in-depth discussion about the technical topics they work on, this difference is notable. Turning around and asking a teammate’s opinion almost always results in a faster, better answer.</p> <p>The downside to this ease of availability is very real, though. Having teams constantly interrupting each other in their work reduces productivity and leads to frustration and a different form of, most often, self-imposed isolation. However, the trade-offs are worth it, and, with some small adjustments, the negatives can be removed entirely. Pinging someone on Slack before asking them a question in person is good way to guage if they are absorbed into their work or if they have time to discuss. Having obvious indicators of whether or not someone can be interrupted can help: headphones on; a marker; an obvious timer.</p> <p>The upsides to overcoming these challenges are huge. Gaining insight from a senior developer on something can save hours or days of work. It can pre-empt a long back-and-forth discussion in the later Code Review step. I’ve been on both the receiving and giving end of both of these many times in the last year. As someone who regularly walks the floor to chat with people, more than once I’ve stepped at a desk and suggested a refactoring or fix that has saved someone several hours of frustration. I’ve also interrupted someone from another team for a few seconds in the coffee room and saved days of work from just a nudge in the right direction.</p> <p>At the end of the day, proximity matters for quality development. Closeness with the engineers that you work with most closely is the primary way you can grow and improve. From the point of view of the company, it also provides enormous benefits in productivity and daily satisfaction. It stimulates growth in developers by allowing them to focus on what matters instead of being mired in minutia. It keeps senior talent from feeling isolated and unable to make the right decisions that keeps the business moving forward. It reduces defects by curtailing implementation problems early in the process. It is absolutely necessary for keeping teams happy and healthy in their work.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the biggest challenges I’ve faced since I’ve moved from being an individual contributor to tech lead has been maintaining my opportunities to work with other senior engineers. My team has undergone significant changes and, as a result, I’m most often the senior member working on any particular feature. While this has had its benefits - mentorship and shared learning through teaching - it’s not the same as daily, 1:1 discussions with extremely experienced engineers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Focus</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/learning-focus/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Focus"/><published>2018-07-28T15:27:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-28T15:27:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/learning-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/learning-focus/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the parts of meditation that interests me the most is building the skill of observing your thoughts. I find this most interesting because it matches the way many other skills are learned; the idea is not to read something, understanding it, and be able to do it; instead, the process requires you to put yourself in a situation over and over again until the process is automatic rather than something you guide youself into.</p> <p>This process of observing your own thoughts can be fairly harrowing. As you begin to meditate, you will notice just how chaotic and free your own thought process is. Controlling it will seem both impossible and painful - holding back one’s own thoughts and actively focusing on something is very challenging. Unless you have an external focus, this process can be very near impossible. Some thoughts will always pop in, frustrating your meditation.</p> <p>This is why this process is all about letting the thoughts come and go. It’s very important to be gentle with your thought process - being a guide rather than a guardsman is how you can make it through. Slowly shifting your thoughts back when they wander off, but not forcing them to stay in a particular place, allows you to eventually narrow the band of what thoughts come in and out.</p> <p>And just like any type of learning, this one needs pool-fulls of practice. And, unlike physical skills, there are less obvious markers of success - there’s no ‘I sunk 15 baskets in a row’ or ‘I got my mile run down under 7’30”’. Like the creative process, this one is more nebulous. But give it time, and make it regular. Even after a few weeks, you’ll find yourself much more focused, and your drifts will come and go more smoothly</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the parts of meditation that interests me the most is building the skill of observing your thoughts. I find this most interesting because it matches the way many other skills are learned; the idea is not to read something, understanding it, and be able to do it; instead, the process requires you to put yourself in a situation over and over again until the process is automatic rather than something you guide youself into.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Gaming Renaissance</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/the-gaming-renaissance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Gaming Renaissance"/><published>2018-07-28T03:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-28T03:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/the-gaming-renaissance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/the-gaming-renaissance/"><![CDATA[<p>I think the boardgame renaissance is one of the most interesting and positive developments in the gaming world in the last decade. From the mediocre world of Monopoly and Risk come fantastic games like Splendor, Mysterium, or Gloomhaven; games that expand the boundaries of what boards games are; games that push back, hard, against the assumption that gaming has to be a stale, regimented process.</p> <p>Traditional games have always been a way to bring people together around a table. I can’t count the number of people I’ve met that tell stories about the times they played Monopoly for hours on end. Or the time their Uno session ended with their grandmother flipping over a table. These are funny anecdotes, but today’s gaming world is much more than that. Today’s board games provide narrative. They provide excitement. They force you to think, to engage, but also to re-evaluate what you think cardboard is capable of.</p> <p>Take a game like Mysterium, a 2015 game designed by Oleksandr Nevskiy and Oleg Sidorenko. At face value, the game is an advanced version of clue - players are guided towards identifying a murderer, a murder location, and a murder weapon that corresponds to their character in the game. A single player plays the ‘ghost’, the guide that provides the clues for the other players. At first glance, the game doesn’t seem particularly deep; building up the clues using the tarot-esque cards provided to the ghost is fun, but that’s about all of it.</p> <p>However, this game is so much more than that. The clue cards are insanely detailed, abstract pieces of art. The process of getting and giving clues relies not only on the available cards, but also the thoughts and tendencies of your fellow players. Both sides - guessers and clue givers - are forced to dive deep into what parts of which clues apply. They must imagine what the thought process of the person playing each part is, on top of the straight facts of the game.</p> <p>What’s more, the game can be warped and changed in many ways that a simpler game like Clue cannot. Have too many players? Have the ‘ghost’ be a whole team of players, sharing clue cards and coming up with a plan to distribute them. Warp the game even further by setting ‘guessers’ on different teams, each with their own ‘ghost’ - share the clue cards, fight over who gives the better clues and gets their team to the finish fastest. Change the nature of the game entirely and have the ‘guessers’ give clues to the ghost, each only able to provide a bit of information at a time - guiding the guide instead.</p> <p>This isn’t to say there’s no way to ‘spice up’ some well-known games. There are many ‘house rules’ around Monopoly, and no less than a dozen ways to mess with Risk. The difference is the scope and ease of adjusting the games of the new era. There is no need to bend over backwards adjusting property prices or messing with dice probability - the tools are all there, ready to use.</p> <p>Adjustability is only one of the many ways games today push the limits - games like 7th Continent redefine what it means to build a narrative in a game, and games like Gloomhaven replace well-known pastimes like Dungeons and Dragons and replace it with a faster pace, easier rules, and a pre-built story and world. Scythe ignores the limits of more traditional strategy games like Risk and Diplomacy, and games like Coup and One Night Ultimate Werewolf and Resistance solve the problems of older games like Mafia.</p> <p>There’s no better time to get into board games, and no better time to be a long-time fan. Every GenCon brings something new, something bold, something exciting. I can’t wait to see what’s next.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I think the boardgame renaissance is one of the most interesting and positive developments in the gaming world in the last decade. From the mediocre world of Monopoly and Risk come fantastic games like Splendor, Mysterium, or Gloomhaven; games that expand the boundaries of what boards games are; games that push back, hard, against the assumption that gaming has to be a stale, regimented process.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intent</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/intent/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intent"/><published>2018-07-26T23:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-26T23:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/intent</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/intent/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the challenges of designings good system, and writing good code in general, is deciding where and when to draw boundaries. Boundaries can be drawn in many ways - deciding to extract something to a class is a form of boundary drawing, as is extracting a method from a conditional. Modules and microservices are the same - just chalk outlines around a piece of functionality that delineates which parts get to hang out together.</p> <p>Getting good at figuring out the boundaries is no small task - however, even when you have a sense of the approximate line, there are details that require significant thought. One of these areas is when to remove duplication for the sake of cleaner lines. I’ll give an example:</p> <p>Some fairly straightforward code.enterScreenis called at some point by some code, and when doing so, it decides based on some condition whether to callgoFromToporgoFromBottom. Now, there is a bit of duplication here - theaddClassmethod is called twice, with the same class. For the sake of a simple argument, let us assume that this class will always be the same.</p> <p>What should we do here? Is this code good? Well, while the answer to the latter is certainly subjective, there is a case to be made for answering the former with: “let’s remove the duplication - remove those methods and do this:”</p> <p>Now, this doesn’t break any hard ‘rules’ - we can still easily test this method, and it’s short enough that it’s clear what’s happening. In addition, it saves us some lines - if we have a ton of code, this might save us a decent chunk of bytes, even in the minified code. However, I think this method is a mistake, as it causes a broader, if less obvious problem.</p> <p>The second code snipper has fuzzier boundaries. In the first snippet, we have drawn a line around our condition -isTop, and made a very declarative statement about what comes after - either we translate something from the bottom, or we translate it from the top. These ‘lines’ are delineations not only in our code organization, but in our verbiage about what the code expressly does. We are marking, very clearly, what the line around ‘translate from the bottom’ and ‘translate from the top’ means. While we are repeating some code, we are clarifying what we consider the boundary - the space between the condition and the code.</p> <p>In our second snipper, we have made this boundary a bit fuzzier. While we still have an obvious condition - isTop, and it’s clear to us what we should do in each case, we don’t have a clear understanding of what happens if this code changes. We also don’t have a clear understanding as to what isimportantin this code. We have been told (mostly) that what is important is that we are entering the screen, and that we have a condition - however, the details are not important. In the former case, we are building a fence around each part of that condition, making it clear that we think each piece is separate and important enough to be given its own chalk outline.</p> <p>This may seem pendantic, but I think it’s a decision that, over time, leads to generally better code. While there are certainly areas where you may want tonotdraw a line around a condition, in my experience most code bases would benefit greatly from that line. All code grows and evolves, but conditionals are where it decays. Drawing thick outlines keeps that decay from spreading - it makes sure that a maintainer of the code is very clear about the intentionality behing the code, not just what’s written on the lines.</p> <p>There are downsides - if you have a large codebase, this could eventually balloon it significantly. If you’re not careful, you could end up with a lot of duplication before it’s obvious that there are components that are capable of reuse. However, I trust in Sandi Metz’s famous mantra - “prefer duplication over the wrong abstraction”. It will save your ass in the long run.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the challenges of designings good system, and writing good code in general, is deciding where and when to draw boundaries. Boundaries can be drawn in many ways - deciding to extract something to a class is a form of boundary drawing, as is extracting a method from a conditional. Modules and microservices are the same - just chalk outlines around a piece of functionality that delineates which parts get to hang out together.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creativity and TDD</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/creativity-and-tdd/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creativity and TDD"/><published>2018-07-25T11:51:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-25T11:51:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/creativity-and-tdd</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/creativity-and-tdd/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the challenges of creativity in programming is being unable to explore code in a way that one explores other forms of art.</p> <p>If you are a painter with a blank canvas, you have many ways of playing around with your paint and your brushes and your pallette to form something you’ve never touched before. You can experiment with changing the angles you use, or painting in a different light, or using a new set of colors or textures. With code, this experimentation sometimes feels out of reach. You can grab a new set of brushes (a new programming language) or a new set of paints (a new type of pattern you’ve learned) but it’s often hard to come up with a new picture. It often feels like you’re coloring by number, only varying the colors.</p> <p>I think test-driven-development is an answer to this challenge of creativity. In particular, London-style TDD is one of the most freeing and though-provoking exercises I’ve done in programming over the last few years.</p> <p>Being able to define the forms and shapes of your code before writing it allows you to pull away from pushing blocks of color together and step out into the outline. By outlining the structure of your code first, you can play with what shape it should eventually take. Like molding clay, this shaping allows you to play with what the final product will be before baking anything. It allows you to go far into the absurd with you APIs, describing and defining them without stepping even a bit into the code itself.</p> <p>This comes with other benefits, as well. By building these shapes and structures ahead of the final product, you can develop more robust code as well. It’s easier to see where the snags and challenges will be when you are building the floor those snags will stick out of. It means you can tell when you are doing something wrong, because when writing out the tests you’ll be writing code thatfeelsodd, rather than just looks it afterwards.</p> <p>Now, all of this is not to say that TDD is the solution to all problems of creativity in software. Code requires a large set of tools to be done well, and learning those tools and understanding them in a way that allows you to experiment quickly without getting stuck in the details is no easy ask. But it is possible, and earning the skill needed to do so is rewarding on its own as well.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the challenges of creativity in programming is being unable to explore code in a way that one explores other forms of art.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Routine</title><link href="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/routine/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Routine"/><published>2018-07-24T11:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-07-24T11:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/routine</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://grobolom.github.io/blog/2018/routine/"><![CDATA[<p>One of the more interesting parts of a morning routine is how much it resembles its own sort of meditation. As I’ve started waking up early in the day and going through a more ritualized set of steps, I’ve found myself feeling the same refreshment and lack of morning mental pressure that I get from meditation.</p> <p>While I am only now starting to incorporate meditation into my rountine, I’ve already found pretty big benefits from it. In particular, meditating during my commute has kept me more focused in the morning. It has caused me to keep my mind off of the distractions and frustrations of the commute, something that is very real given the three-quarters of an hour I spend in a tiny space with hundreds of other commuters.</p> <p>This morning routine has other benefits, though the most striking are the improvements in my day from just the different travel time. Getting to the station at 6 rather than 8 means a few hundred less people to share the train with, as well as a few dozen more empty seats available. Getting off on the right foot each morning is very important to keeping your day feeling good and productive; having to start that day feeling cramped and crowded or having to spend most of it upright, waiting for a transfer is not conducive to these feelings.</p> <p>The other advantage of the early rise is the lack of general distractions, though this is something other have written about at length and with more eloquent expression. That said, it’s important to remind yourself just how many emails, text, and phonecalls you avoid from breaking your flow by just moving to a part of the day where those things don’t exist. The vast majority of your coworkers and friends will not be awake with you at 6 am, and even if they are, the last thing they will be thinking off is what to text you.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tumblr-archive"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[One of the more interesting parts of a morning routine is how much it resembles its own sort of meditation. As I’ve started waking up early in the day and going through a more ritualized set of steps, I’ve found myself feeling the same refreshment and lack of morning mental pressure that I get from meditation.]]></summary></entry></feed>